Guide to the Hazel Marie Hauck papers, 1924-1960.
Hauck, Hazel Marie papers, 1924-1960
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Hazel Marie Hauck papers, 1924-1960.
23-14-730
Hazel Marie Hauck, 1900-1964.
2.4 cubic feet.
Correspondence, diaries, notes, reports, pamphlets, articles, photographs, theses, and course material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence with former students and Cornell administrators; her Nigerian diaries and manuscript and typescript notes and statistical reports, and pamphlets concerning nutrition and disease in Thailand, Nigeria, and elsewhere; articles by Hauck concerning her work in those countries and general problems of nutrition; photographs of Thai and Nigerian children, showing the effects of malnutrition; her M.A. and Ph.D. theses; and notes, syllabi, reading lists, and other material relating to courses she taught at Cornell University.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Hazel Hauck received her Ph.D. in 1932 with a major in nutrition and a minor in medical science from the University of Wisconsin and that same year was hired by Cornell as Assistant Professor. She was promoted to the rank of full Professor in 1936.
She served in the Department of Food and Nutrition in the New York State College of Home Economics for twenty-nine years, and was a member of the faculty of the Graduate School of Nutrition from the time of its establishment in 1941 until her retirement in 1961. She did research in the Cornell-in-Thailand Project, 1952-1953 and in the Village Improvement and Leadership Training Program of the Unitarian Service Committee in Awo Amamma, Eastern Nigeria, 1959-1960.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence with former students and Cornell administrators; her Nigerian diaries (5 volumes, 1959-1960) and manuscript and typescript notes and statistical reports, and pamphlets concerning nutrition and disease in Thailand, Nigeria, and elsewhere; articles by Hauck concerning her work in those countries and general problems of nutrition; photographs of Thai and Nigerian children, showing the effects of malnutrition; her M.A. and Ph.D. theses (University of Washington, 1924; University of Wisconsin, 1932), "A Study of the Cause of Failure of a Specific Ration" and "Manifestations of Fluorine Toxicity"; and notes, syllabi, reading lists, and other material relating to courses she taught at Cornell University.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Hauck, Hazel Marie, 1900-1964.; American Unitarian Association. Unitarian Service Committee. Village Improvement and Leadership Training Program.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University. Cornell-in-Thailand Project.
Subjects:
Deficiency diseases--Nigeria.; Deficiency diseases--Thailand.; Diseases--Nigeria.; Diseases--Thailand.; Malnutrition--Nigeria.; Malnutrition--Thailand.; Nutrition--Research--Nigeria.; Nutrition--Research--Thailand.; Women--Diaries.; College teachers.; Nutritionists.
Places:
Nigeria.; Thailand.
Form and Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Photographs - 169 negatives, 295 photographs (headings to some) Includes "Food Habits and Nutrient Intakes in a Siamese Rice Village - Studies in Bang Chen, 1942-1954" (Box 1)
- "Federal Nigeria", 1960-11-1960-12 (Box 1)
- Includes photos of Stella Cheng of Cornell (1944): Dr. W.J. Meek and Dr. Walter Bradford Cannon; Dr. Mary Schwartz Rose, Columbia University (1940); Dr. Lauriston Sharp, Cornell; Animal Nutrition Seminars held at Cornell, 1940-1949 (Box 1)
- Book of rough notes - half foreign (Box 2)
- Book of council school records - adults, No. V (Box 2)
- Diary and notes on childbirth in Awo Omamma, child loss rate, weight change, diet, antenatal clinics, growth and feeding practices, No. IX, May 31 (1959) (Box 2)
- Clinic records and notes - re: pregnancy and acceptability test - ground nut flour - given 30g 1 person, No. VI (Box 2)
- School records,and antenatal clinic, No. IV, 1960 (Box 2)
- Diary, No.VII, 1960-02-1960-05-31 (Box 2)
- Diary, and four pages rough index, No. II, 1959-10-20-1959-12-12 (Box 2)
- Diary, No. III, 1959-12-13-1960-02-14 (Box 2)
- Diary - Menu - Index, No. I, 1959-09-19-1959-10-20 (Box 2)
- Folder of pamphlets
  - The effect of fluorine feeding on the storage of vitamin C in the rat and guinea pig, by Hazel M. Hauck (Box 2)
  - Is the effect of fluorine on teeth produced through the parathyroid glands? by Hazel M. Hauck, Harry Steenbock and Helen T. Parsons (Box 2)
  - The effect of the level of calcium intake on the calcification of bones and teeth during fluorine toxicosis, by Hazel M. Hauck, Harry Steenbock and Helen T. Parsons (Box 2)
  - Effect of fluorine on growth, calcification and parathyroids in the chicken, by Hazel M. Hauck, H. Steenbock and James T. Lowe, and J.G. Halpin (Box 2)
- Manifestations of fluorine toxicity, by Hazel Marie Hauck - A thesis submitted for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy. University of Wisconsin, 1932 (Box 2)
- A folder M.A. Thesis - A study of the cause of failure of a specific ration, by Hazel M. Hauck. Submitted for the degree of Master of Arts - University of Washington, 1924 (Box 2)
- Folder - Special feature articles (Box 3)
- Pamphlet - Health statistics from the U.S. National Health Survey, series B, No. 21 (Box 3)
- Diabetes reported in interviews, United States, 1957-07-1959-06 (Box 3)
- Pamphlet - Health statistics from the U.S. National Health Survey, series B, No. 17, Peptic Ulcers, reported in interviews, United States, 1957-07-1959-06 (Box 3)
- Journal of the American Dietetic Association, Vol. 35, Number 11, 1959-11 (Box 3)
- List of Publications - Hazel M. Hauck (Box 3)
- Article - Tests for fastness to light of dyed fabrics, by Hazel M. Hauck, Dept. of Household Arts, University of Oregon (Box 3)
- Paper clipping - Cinderella of Vegetables, by Hazel M. Hauck - from New York Herald Tribune (Box 3)
- Paper clipping "Textile Expert" by Hazel M. Hauck (Box 3)
- Paper clipping "How Bon Marche Knows Wool and Silk Percentages, from Good Merchants Trade Journal - picture of Hazel M. Hauck - (2 pcs.) (Box 3)
- Summaries of Research in food and nutrition, by Hazel M. Hauck. (2 pcs.) from "Signs of the Times" (Box 3)
- Paper clipping - Are you sure of what you're Buying? by Hazel M. Hauck - Retail Ledger - Philadelphia, 1924-06 (Box 3)
- Article - Written for Food and Health Education - Home making, not Housekeeping the object in University of North Dakota Practice House, by Hazel M. Hauck, Instructor in Home Economics, University of North Dakota (Box 3)
- Letter, from Hazel M. Hauck to Mrs. Mary P. Huddleston, and article - Nutrition Problems of Maturity and Old Age, 1936-11-12 (Box 3)
- A Manual for Writers of term papers, theses and dissertations, by Kate L. Turabian (Box 3)
- Pamphlet - L'Enseignment Menager - Home Economics, Hauswirtschaftsunterricht, 1961-06 (Box 3)
- Envelope of name tabs for Miss Hauck's books (Box 3)
- Pamphlet - Food and Health 2. Food for Energy, Hazel M. Hauck, reported from Today's Health, 1957-11 (Box 3)
- 1 folder - Personal Inventories, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
- 1 folder - Nigeria - article - "The Magic in a Peanut" by H.M.H., 1960-10-10 (Box 3)
- Letter from Deane W. Malott - pamphlet - Venture, 1958 (Box 3)
  Autumn
- Folder - Celiac Disease and Sprue (Box 3)
- Folder - Epilepsy (Box 3)
- Folder - Anemia Pernicious (Box 3)
- Envelope - Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station - Food and Nutrition. State Project, Number 17, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
- Folder - Seminar Ideas (Box 3)
- Envelope to Professor Hazel M. Hauck from Flemmie P. Kittrell - Howard University, Washington, D.C. (Box 3)
- Folder - Food and Nutrition 400 - Pellagra - Ditto (Box 3)
- Folder - Food and Nutrition 400 - B 12 and Pernicious Anemia (Box 3)
- Folder - Home Economics Alumnae letters - Cornell - Milestone in History at Cornell (Box 3)
- Folder - Nigeria - Customs (Box 3)
- Folder - Obstetrics - Hanks (Box 3)
- Folder - Data Papers - Maternal and Infant Nutrition (Box 3)
- Appendix A - Description of the Kitchen and Some Notes on Food Preparation in a Relatively Prosperous Household (Box 3)
- Folder - Heights and Weights of School Children BC (Box 3)
- Folder - School Children - by age and sex, 1948-1949 (Box 3)
- Folder - Analysis Notes (Box 3)
- Folder - School Lists - Bang Chan, 1952-1953 (Box 3)
- Folder - HH - Wt. - Age Tables, B.C. School Children- complete data, 1949 (Box 3)
- Folder - Concerning School children, 1952-1953 (Box 3)
- Folder - Pratoms 3a, 3b, 4a, 4b, 1952-12 (Box 3)
- Folder - Pratoms 3a, 3b, 4, 4a, 4b, 1953-02 (Box 3)
- Folder - Letter from Nigeria written for Rural Missions, by H.M.H. (Box 4)
- Folder - Article by Vannevar Bush (10 copies) "The Builders" (Box 4)
- Folder - Growth in heigh and weight of Thai infants and young children. List of people reprint to be sent to (Box 4)
- Correspondence to and from H.M.H. Book reviews (Box 4)
- Folder - Nigeria - Plans for talks - Preliminary Report of Observations on Health and Diet (Box 4)
- Awo Omamma, Nigeria, Hazel M. Hauck, Field Consultant, Unitarian Service Committee, Inc., 1959-1960 (Box 4)
- Folder - Serendipity - Animal Nutrition Seminar,(9 pcs.), 1949-02-21 (Box 4)
- Folder - Vitamin History - New York State College of Home Economics at Cornell University, Ithaca, New York (Box 4)
- Food and Nutrition 420, Some Landmarks in the History of Vitamin B. - Preface to Pereira's Treatise on Food and Diet (1843), 1945-12-14, 1945-12-21 (Box 4)
- Article - Taken from "The Analyst and the Medical Man" by F. Gowland Hopkins, The Analyst Vol. 31, 1906 (Box 4)
- Folder - Vitamin G - Nicotinic Acid, Pellagra (Box 4)
- Pamphlet - United States Treasury Dpt. Public Health Reports, also articles on Pellagra among chronic alcoholic addicts, 1934-06-29 (Box 4)
- Folder - Vitamin B 12 - Treatment of Pernicious Anemia (Box 4)
- Folder - Graduate Students - miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Folder - Newsletters (4 copies) (Box 4)
- Folder - Misc. - Faculty Minutes - pamphlet re: Farm Labor in under developed economies - charts - correspondence - Paper clipping, article on Japan, Thailand - Graduate School of Nutrition News, Cornell University, 1 page, 1959-12 (Box 4)
- Folder - Personal - Appointment - Leaves of Absences - Attendance at meetings. (Box 4)
- Folder - Letters - mostly from old students (Box 4)
- Envelope - Memorandum and extracts from memoranda (Box 4)
- Folder - History of Nutrition I - Introduction: Fats, Bile, Transformation of Food to Meat and Milk, page 16-21, Missing. (Box 4)
- History of Nutrition AH 215 (Plan for Course 215), 1953 (Box 4)
  Fall
- Folder - History of Nutrition - McCay complete set (Box 4)
- Folder - History of Nutrition, 1946 (Box 5)
- Folder - History of Food and Nutrition - Books (Box 5)
- Folder - Animal Nutrition 215 - Amino Acids and Proteins (Box 5)
- Folder - History of Nutrition - McCay pH; Special topics on protein (Box 5)
- Folder - Nucleo proteins (Box 5)
- Folder - Notes - Drummond - The Englishman's Food (Box 5)
- Folder - Men in Agricultural Chemistry - (Misc.) (Box 5)
- Book - Kwashiorkor in Africa -FAO Nutritional Studies, No. 8, 1952-03 (Box 5)
- Book - Protein Malnutrition in Brazil, FAO Nutritional Studies, No. 14, 1956-03 (Box 5)
- Book - Calorie Requirements. FAO Nutritional Studies, No. 15, 1957 (Box 5)
- Book - The Urease - (Reprinted from Journal of Chemical Education. Vol. 14. No. 6.) James B. Sumner, Medical College, Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.), 1937-06 (Box 5)
- Folder - League of Nations - Nutrition (Box 5)
- Folder - Pacific Science Conference Paper and Correspondence (Box 5)
- Folder - Journal Tropical Pediatrics, 1960-12 (Box 5)
- Folder - Persons to whom data paper #3a have gone, 1960 (Box 5)
- Folder - Persons to whom Technical Report of H.M. Hauck Field Consultant for USC, should be sent (Box 5)
- Folder - List of People to receive Data Paper on Diet #29, 1958 (Box 5)
- Folder - Reprint requests, Data Paper 22, 1956 (Box 5)
- Nutrition in the Ill-fed and Underdeveloped Countries of the World. Dr. Hazel M. Hauck - College of Home Economics, Cornell University, 1958-03-11 (Box 5)
- Folder - Notes for Field Research Workers Outlines of Studies (Box 5)
- Folder - Talks on Thailand - Outlines (Box 5)
- Folder - Fulbright Grant Miscellaneous Information (Box 5)
- Folder - Miscellaneous Clippings, etc. (Box 5)
- Folder - Fulbright Reports, etc., 1952-09-08, 1953-01 (Box 5)
- Folder - Missionary Courses - Announcements (Box 5)
- Folder - Holmes Medical Essays (Excerpts) (Box 5)
- Folder - Anemia Pernicious (Box 5)
- Folder - Nephritis (Box 5)
- Folder - Diabetic Diets, Historical (Box 5)
- Folder - Diabetes in Children (Box 5)
- Folder - Diabetes, General (Box 5)
- Folder - Surgery in Diabetes (Box 5)
- Folder - Saccharin, Sucaryl (Box 5)
- Folder - Typhoid Fever (Box 5)
- Folder - Gastric Function and Disturbances - Peptic Ulcer (Box 5)
- Folder - Apple Diet in Diarrhea (Box 5)
- Folder - Pratoms 3, 4a,, 4b, 1953-05 (Box 6)
- Folder - Pratoms 3, 4a, 1953-07 (Box 6)
- Folder - Pratoms 3, 4, 1953-09 (Box 6)
- Folder - Pratoms 3, 4, 1953-10 (Box 6)
- Folder - Pratoms 3, 4, 1953-11 (Box 6)
- Folder - Pratoms 3, 4, 1954-01 (Box 6)
- Folder - Pratoms 3, 4, 1954-06 (Box 6)
- Folder - Rough Summaries by Grades - School Children (Box 6)
- Folder - Schedules - Mothers and Babies (Box 6)
- Folder - Schedules of Visits to Babies (Box 6)
- Folder - Tables of Measurement of Infants (Box 6)
- Folder - Notes re: Schedule 4 and 5 and Supplement (Mothers and Babies) (Box 6)
- Folder - Anothais material (Box 6)
- Folder - Blank Schedules - Mothers (Box 6)
- Folder - Summary of Physical Examination of Persons in Dietary Survey (Box 6)
- Folder - Data on Older Children not in Surgery (Box 6)
- Folder - Material used in preparation of Schedule 3 - Medical Exam (Box 6)
- Folder - Clinical Survey (Box 6)
- Folder - Clinical Examination (Box 6)
- Folder - Clinical Examination and Family Dietary Studies - Plan (Box 6)
- Folder - Physical Examination of Individual Persons in Dietary Survey - Group A (Box 6)
- Folder - Physical Examination of Individual Persons in Dietary Survey - Group B (Box 6)
- Folder - Summary of association of signs and symptoms of BC school children (Box 6)
- Folder - Summary of association of signs and symptoms of BC family survey (random survey) (Box 6)
- Folder - Tables - Height and Weight (Box 6)
- Folder - Bang Chan structured questionnaire (Box 7)
- Folder - Height - Weight data from School Hygiene (Box 7)
- Folder - Weight, Tables to 19 years (Box 7)
- Folder - Bang Chan - Jane R. Hanks (Box 7)
- Folder - Diphtheria Immunization in a Thai Community (Box 7)
- Folder - Household Questionnaire - (Hanks), 1954-03-1954-04 (Box 7)
- Folder - Population - Bang Chan (Box 7)
- Folder - Bangkok - File Index (Box 7)
- Folder - Food Sanitation - Condensed Schedule 8 Dietary Survey (Box 7)
- Folder - Heights and Weights - Siamese Men and Women - Fen Yong and Laong (Box 7)
- Folder - Gaps in Data (Box 7)
- Folder - Notes re: data, Coding procedures etc. Schedule 3 (Box 7)
- Folder - Code lists (Box 7)
- Folder - Information from K.J.'s Study (Box 7)
- Folder - Draft from Part III, Health and Diet (Bang Chan), 1948-1949 (Box 7)
- Folder - Intestinal Parasites (Box 7)
- Folder - Notes on Illness and Toilet facilities (Box 7)
- Folder - Field Notes - Bang Chan - Hazel M. Hauck, 1952-1953 (Box 7)
- Folder - Midwifery Notes (Box 7)
- Folder - Field Notes - SS (Box 7)
- Folder - Growth of School and Infants and Young Children (2 papers) - J. Trop, Pediatrics (Box 8)
- Folder - Tables re: nutri-status - children and families (Box 8)
- Folder - Med-inspection (for comparison with diet) (Box 8)
- Folder - Professor Hauck (Box 8)
- Envelope - containing Betel Leaves (Box 8)
- Folder - Ideas on R------g? '60 - Kertesz (Box 8)
- Reprint from the Editorial Department of the Journal of the American Medical Association, Vol. 152, 1537 - FOOD AND PREVENTIVE MEDICINE, 1953-08-15 (Box 8)
- Paper on Nutrition in Chronic Renal Failure, by Arthur J. Merrill, M.D., Atlanta, Ga. (Box 8)
- Cornell Extension Bulletin 670 - Food Value Chart - Grace Steininger and Hazel M. Hauck (Box 8)
- Card - Platt. B. S. (Box 8)
- Paper - Reprint From The Journal of The American Medical Association, Effect of Alcohol on the Liver, by Gerald Klatskin, M.D., New Haven, Conn., 1959-08-01 (Box 8)
- Paper - Food for Homage-to-the-Teacher Rite Performed by a Buddhist Priest who was a Traditional Practitioner (Box 8)
- Folder - Types of "with rice" dishes prepared by families in diet survey. - Rounds I-IV, Groups A and B (Box 8)
- Folder - Copies of Dietary Surveys - Round I (consisting of notes re: kind and amount of food eaten and method of preparation.) Inc. (Box 8)
- Folder - Summary of Meal Patterns, by Rounds, (All Families, 2 groups) (Box 8)
- Folder - Food terms and glossary - Data Paper (Box 8)
- Folder - Nutrition Value, for each family (Box 8)
- Folder - Dietary Calc. - SS, BS and HMH (Box 8)
- Book - Ethiopia - Nutrition Survey, 1959-09 (Box 8)
- Book - H.M. Hauck - Notes, BC, Book - H.M. Hauck - Notes, Book II - Bang Chan; 1952-1953; 1953 (Box 8)
- Book - Nutritional Problems in Medicine - Symposium, 6 (Box 8)
- Letter and Book - Cornell Program in Social Psychiatry. Second Annual Report (Box 8)